Do you ever wake up with a fuzzy feeling in your head, you can't concentrate on anything, or find your memory just isn't working as it should?
你是否曾在醒来时感到头脑昏沉，无法集中注意力，或者发现记忆力不如往常？
You're not alone.
你并不孤单。
39% of British people said they suffer brain fog on a regular basis in a FutureYou Cambridge study.
FutureYou剑桥研究显示，39%的英国人表示他们经常遭受脑雾的困扰。
But why do we get brain fog, and can we do anything to prevent it?
但我们为什么会出现脑雾，我们能做些什么来预防它呢？
The technical word for brain fog is cognitive impairment.
脑雾的专业术语是认知障碍。
When you have it, you can't think as clearly as you normally can – just as if your brain was actually full of fog.
当你有脑雾时，你无法像往常那样清晰地思考——就好像你的大脑真的充满了雾。
Dr Brennan, a neuroscientist and author, says "Brain fog is different to these short-term disruptions, because it is persistent, occurs regularly and can interfere with the quality of your life, your relationships, and your work".
神经科学家兼作家布伦南博士说："脑雾与这些短期干扰不同，因为它是持续性的，经常发生，并且会干扰你的生活质量、人际关系和工作。"
The reality is that no-one knows exactly what causes it, though theories include chemical or blood flow changes in the brain, and low-level inflammation.
事实是，没有人确切知道是什么导致了脑雾，尽管有一些理论涉及大脑中的化学或血流变化，以及低度炎症。
What we do know are factors that make it worse.
我们所知道的是那些会使情况恶化的因素。
Fatigue, for example, is a key contributor to brain fog, making it hard to stay focused.
例如，疲劳是导致脑雾的一个关键因素，使人难以保持专注。
This is because sleep deficiency can change activity in some parts of the brain, which means processing and recalling detail becomes harder.
这是因为睡眠不足可以改变大脑某些部分的活动，这意味着处理和回忆细节变得更加困难。
Pain and anxiety can also contribute to it – they interfere with cognitive speed because they are distracting.
疼痛和焦虑也可能导致脑雾——它们会干扰认知速度，因为它们会分散注意力。
There are also medical conditions that can make it worse, like long Covid or autoimmune conditions like lupus disease.
还有一些医疗状况会使情况恶化，比如长新冠（新冠后遗症）或狼疮等自身免疫性疾病。
So, if you're suffering from brain fog, what can you do to fix it?
那么，如果你正遭受脑雾的困扰，你能做些什么来解决它呢？
One thing you can do is avoid ultra-processed foods (UPFs).
你可以做的一件事是避免超加工食品。
Dr Megan Rossi, the founder of The Gut Health Doctor, told the BBC that "UPFs are often low in essential nutrients like magnesium, omega-3 fatty acids and iron, all of which are crucial for brain function and mental clarity".
肠道健康医生创始人梅根·罗西博士告诉BBC："超加工食品通常缺乏镁、欧米伽-3脂肪酸和铁等必需营养素，而所有这些都对大脑功能和思维清晰至关重要。"
Therefore, we should pack our diets with nutrient-rich foods like whole grains, vegetables and healthy fats.
因此，我们应该在饮食中多摄入营养丰富的食物，如全谷物、蔬菜和健康脂肪。
Blueberries are particularly rich in polyphenols and have been shown to improve cognitive function and memory in clinical trials.
蓝莓尤其富含多酚，在临床试验中已被证明可以改善认知功能和记忆力。
Hydration is also very important.
补水也非常重要。
So, if you feel a bit foggy, try to get more sleep and consider making some changes to your diet.
所以，如果你感觉有点昏沉，试着多睡一会儿，并考虑改变一下你的饮食。